In crossover, which may happen in several different
ways, corresponding bits of the parent strings are swapped to produce new chromosomes.
In order to guarantee the genetic diversity of a new population, in addition
to crossover, mutation is applied which modifies elements of the symbol strings in
various ways by using stochastic procedures.

In principle, the scheme of a genetic algorithm is structured as follows:
1. Generate random starting population of n chromosomes
2. Calculate the fitness of each chromosome If good enough, dump the result, END
Else:
3. The fittest chromosomes are transferred unmodified or undergo crossover or mutation
4. Select a number of fittest chromosomes as starting individuals
5. Create next generation and repeat from step 2

In “Genetic Algorithms in Search, Optimization and Machine Learning” [16],
David Goldberg describes an example [16, p. 7–19] of a simple application of a
genetic algorithm. Consider a black box system which produces a numeric output
for different positions of its switches (figure 7.2). When the switches are represented
as binary symbol sequences (chromosomes), numerical values result in particular
positions that may also be used to determine a simple fitness function: The higher a
chromosome’s numeric value, the better its fitness.
Fig. 7.2 Black box, output and fitness values (rightmost is % of sum of total fitness) [16, p. 8, 11].
c 1989 Pearson Education Inc. Reproduced by permission.
160 7 Genetic Algorithms
Now, every chromosome’s fitness is allotted (according to Goldberg) to the segments
of a so-called “roulette wheel” (figure 7.3) in order to select chromosomes
that may be used for crossover by creating weighted probabilities:
Fig. 7.3 Probabilities for the selection of chromosomes in crossover [16, p. 11]. c 1989 Pearson
Education Inc. Reproduced by permission.


Because the search space is restricted by binary symbol strings to a value between
0 0 0 0 0 and 1 1 1 1 1, each chromosome x has a possible value between 0 and
31. The function underlying the black box is assumed to be f (x) = x2. Suppose a
population consists of four chromosomes (strings) whose initial configuration may
be acquired by flipping a coin twenty times. In the following example, the values of
the black box are applied. After generating the initial population, values as given in
figure 7.4 result; the columns 3 to 6 indicate the following:
• x : Value of the binary string in decimal notation.
• f (x) = x2 : Value of the chromosome in regards to the fitness function.
• fi/Σf : Relation of the single values to the total sum.
• fi/f : Relation of the single chromosome values to the average of all chromosomes.
• Actual count from Roulette Wheel: The results of the roulette wheel with regard
to the selection of the chromosomes used for crossover.

The production of a new population starts with the selection of chromosomes,
to which crossover will be applied. In this example (figure 7.4), chromosome 1 and
chromosome 4 are selected once, chromosome 2 is selected twice, and chromosome
3 is not selected at all. These chromosomes (first column in figure 7.5) are now
crossed-over with randomly selected chromosomes (second column in figure 7.5) at
a randomly chosen crossover point and result in new chromosomes; this process is
referred to as one-point crossover. As a result of this crossover, the sum, the average,
and the highest achieved value of single chromosomes have increased in regard
to the fitness function. Dispensing with mutation, this example shows some basic
operations of genetic algorithms that, however, may be expanded upon in different
ways. se side 161.

